Living life in moderation
I'm really curious whether it's possible
for human beings to take the middle path.
I wouldn't dare use the term 'middle path,'
but would rather the word 'moderation.'
I'm not referring to moderation as in
getting things over and done with,
but rather moderation that makes
things just right and adequate.
I think that such a state of moderation
is the most beautiful thing.
If there's one thing I seek in life,
it is to live a life of that beauty.
And yet I notice that as
I grow older and try harder,
it doesn't get easier but only harder.
Even at my workplace,
such difficulties torment me.
I now find myself in a position
where I need to assess and advise others.
Being in such a position, I realize that
my humbleness doesn't come as a virtue,
but rather a frustration to others.
While I've also thought that my preparedness
and cautiousness were strengths of mine,
such qualities were being regarded by
others as being indecisive and inflexible.
I tried hard, yet it wasn't adequate.
Hence I don't know how else I should try.
As I try to make efforts,
I have to go against my nature and
superficially mingle with others.
Doing this is hard for me, having to
say unnatural and superficial things.
And as it's superficial, it doesn't
come out well. Neither is it beautiful.
I wonder how I can seek the middle path,
between living in peace
and in my natural state,
and living fiercely and to the fullest.
Just live as it comes.
You're mentally obsessing over it,
this we'd call an intellectual
obsessing disorder.
Just as some feel anxious over a disorganized
household, you have a mental obsession.
It's a disorder, it's far from
taking the middle path.
If you intend to fix this disorder,
don't fret over things too much.
Don't try too hard.
Then you'll get back onto the middle path.
What you're currently thinking as
a middle path is defined by an obsession.
If this is a result of reading my books,
then don't read my books ever again.
You're going further away
from my intentions.
Close the books, and live life as it comes.
Be ok with others speaking badly about you.
The true meaning of taking the middle path
is all about moderately slanting left and right.
If you absolutize that there should be
no swaying, you're already swaying.
You have to allow yourself to slant a bit.
Only then can you take the middle path.
Depending on the time, place, and situation,
conditions are bound to change.
Hence it's difficult to say
anything is 100% absolute.
You should allow yourself to moderately
swing left and right to a certain degree.
Only then can you live in true moderation.
In short, live as it comes.
You're mentally obsessing over it,
it's like an illness.
If you live with such an obsession,
the people around you will feel frustrated.
You'll be trying hard to live a beautiful life,
and yet to others it won't look all that beautiful.
You'll be trying to live a good life,
but to others you won't be living well.
You'll think you're living free,
but you'll ultimately find yourself trapped.
It's likely to be this way.
There is this saying, "If you call it 'the way',
then it's already not the way."
You're already slanting by obsessing.
Obsessing is neither 'the way,'
nor the middle path.
If you expect compensation for your efforts,
that itself is far from the middle path.
If you're making efforts for the sake of
compensation, you're a slave to compensation.
You are bound by the compensation.
Being conscious of other people's
perspectives is a life of a slave.
Hence when I say 'live as it comes,'
it applies to everything.
Don't be conscious of what
other people think of you.
And while you can live your life as you want,
you shouldn't live it the way you want at all times.
There are things that you may want,
and things that you don't want.
There are also things that you should do,
and things you shouldn't.
That’s situational ethics.
At times they mismatch.
So putting them together,
you get 4 alternatives.
Things you want to do and should do.
This has no issue. You can proceed with them.
Things you don't want to do and shouldn't do.
This again has no issue, no need to proceed.
However, there are things you want, yet shouldn't do.
There are also things you don't want, yet should do.
For these, you have to go against
your heart and put some will into it.
Why? Because it will do you less harm.
Now if you're willing to accept the karma,
then it's fine.
For example, let's say you see a pretty
girl pass by, you want to grasp her.
You can grasp her, as long as you're
willing to go to jail for three years.
You shouldn't be resentful in this case.
You should think, 'Back in the Chosun period,
I would've been jailed 10 years.
These days I'm only sentenced 3 years.'
With such a mindset, you can do whatever
as long as you're willing to pay the price.
If your actions don't harm others,
no need to think too much.
And yet who's at a loss to be jailed
for 3 years for an impulsive grasp?
It's ultimately your loss, hence you
don't do it even if you want to.
That's not going against your nature.
In the same manner, there are instances
when it's ok to vent anger when angry.
There are other instances when
venting will result in a big loss.
In the latter case, you should smile on
the outside even when frustrated
on the inside. Do you understand?
That's not going against your nature.
It's only seeking what's right for yourself.